<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon the late King James's declaration, lately dispersed by the Jacobites</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58384</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11893729</idno>
  <idno type="VID">50509</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240893917</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R730</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6321</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11893729</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58384)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50509)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 507:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon the late King James's declaration, lately dispersed by the Jacobites</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The declaration is dated April 20, 1692.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701. --  His Majesties most gracious declaration to all his loving subjects, commanding their assistance against the P. of Orange, and his adherents.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50509:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS UPON THE Late King <hi>JAMES</hi>'s DECLARATION, Lately Dispersed by the Jacobites.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50509:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50509:2"/>
            <head>Reflections upon the late King <hi>James</hi>'s De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE late Revolution of Government in these Three Kingdoms, has carried along with it so many Blessings to these Nations, and the rest of Christendom, both with respect to the Civil Rights of all, and the Religious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of all that profess themselves Protestants, that none but such as are professed Enemies to Humane Laws, and consequently to all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but that of an Absolute Monarchy, which is a Plain Downright Tyranny, and to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of the Protestant Religion, can be uneasie under it, and refrain from Hearty Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the Divine Goodness for suffering it to be brought about, when (God knows) we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served no such Mercy at his Hands, but to fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitied under all the Calamities we had in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, and which many of us had been so Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in bringing upon our selves. And the Remarkable Providences that attended it, and have so signally appear'd, both in the Preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of His Majesty's Person, formerly and now of late, and in the Success of his Arms, have been such, as to be only inferior to those recorded in Sacred Writ, concerning the Delivery of the People of <hi>Israel</hi> from the Salvery they were under
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50509:3"/>to the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> And yet as there were Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murers among them, whom nothing would please but to make themselves a Captain and return into <hi>Egypt:</hi> So, to the Reproach of this Age and Nation, we have Grumblers amongst us, who ever since the Revolution, have been Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating with the Open and Professed Enemies of their Country, their Religion, and the Civil Rights of all Nations, to undo all that has been done, and to bring us back again, not into the same, but a far Worse, and much more De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable, because Irretrieveable, Estate of Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness and Misery, than that was, from which it pleased God to rescue us in so unexampl'd a manner.</p>
            <p>Their Folly and Madness in hoping to mend their own Condition, or that of the Nation, by another Change of Government, is so Stupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, that I shall say nothing of it; for Men that can be so near the Level of Brutes, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve any Benefit can accrue to this Nation, by returning like a Dog to its Vomit, are uncapable of being argued with, perswaded to, or inform'd of any thing whatsoever. And if they know and believe, which they must do, if they are capable of knowing and believing any thing, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stauration of the late King <hi>James</hi> by the Power of <hi>France,</hi> would be the utter Ruin (to all Humane Appearance) of the Laws, Liberties and Religion now established and professed in and by this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50509:3"/>Nation; their execrable Villany in engaging in so Black a Conspiracy, is such as must render them Odious to God and Man, as being no better than very Devils in Humane Shape.</p>
            <p>But since common Charity inclines me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no Men do Mischief for Mischief's sake, I can more easily pronounce them Fools than Knaves; and the design of this Paper, is to prove them to be Fools by the greatest Instance of their Folly, that has yet appear'd in publick, Which is a Declaration Printed and Published here, in the Name of the late King <hi>James,</hi> inviting all his Loving Subjects to return to their Duty and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and to assist him against the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and his Adherents.</p>
            <p>That Pretended Declaration has been Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>striously dispersed in several Places in and about this Town, and that very lately, even since the Fleets were engaged, but before the News came to Town of their Majesties Success; and an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertisement written upon it, that the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Dutch Fleets</hi> were Worsted. By which we see not only how Industrious they are in the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of their Design, but how great Assurance they had of Accomplishing their Execrable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; not questioning, but that through Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery in our Fleet, the French would prevail, and then the Sea being open, the Troops in <hi>Normandy</hi> prepar'd for a Descent upon <hi>England,</hi> would
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50509:4"/>presently be wafted over, with the late King <hi>James</hi> at the Head of them, who would have little or nothing to do, by reason of the Force he was to bring with him, the Assistance that was prepar'd for him here, and his supposed Interest in our Army (which I presume is much the same with what they perswaded him he had in the Navy) but to take Possession of what the <hi>Coxcombs</hi> call his Right. But as they have hitherto been Baffled in all their other Attempts, so they are at present (Thanks be to Almighty God) in this greatest and last Effort they will ever be able to make. The Defeat of the <hi>French Fleet</hi> has dash'd all their Expectations; and it is to be presumed, has rendred them and their Interest as Despicable in the Eyes of their Patron <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. as they were before in the Eyes of all Wise and Honest Men. Insomuch that I know not whether it be now worth while to offer at an Answer to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Declaration, or at making any Reflections upon it, which has received so very seasonable, so full, and so late an Answer from Providence it self. Yet having design'd to say something to it from the first time I got a sight of it, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving perused it carefully in order thereunto, I am not willing to be balk'd of my Fancy, though they are of theirs: And this Benefit at least may redound to the Nation by exposing it, to wit, the enabling them to set a greater Value upon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50509:4"/>the Mercy of God, in frustrating the Hellish Design that was formed against them, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting them even from the Invitation that was made to them in the late King's Name, to return to their Allegiance, what a Condition they were like to be in under his Government.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the Pen-men of this Declaration, might have done their Cause as much Service by the Publishing of it without any mention of the <hi>French King</hi> at all, as they are like to do by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging in the Introduction to it, <hi>The Promises made by him to the late King, to assist him in the Recovery of his Kingdoms, as soon as the Condition of his own Affairs would permit it: And the French King's lending him so many Troops as may be suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to unty the Hands of his Subjects, and make it Safe for them to return to their Duty, and repair to his Standard.</hi> They cannot but know how Odious the <hi>French Tyrant</hi> is to the People of this Nation, and they ought to know that it is Just he should be so; for that both we and all his Neighbors look upon it, as one of the Dreadfullest Calamities that in an ordinary course of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence can befall a Nation, to come under his Power, or lye at his Mercy. The Friendship be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the late King and <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. was none of the least Disgusts that his Government gave to the Nation; we look'd upon our selves as reserved to be swallowed up last, when by his Successes upon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50509:5"/>the Continent, and the daily Increase of his Power by Sea, he should be grown too Powerful for us to Cope with. A War against <hi>France</hi> was the Cry of the Nation for some Years; and now that we have a War with <hi>France,</hi> a War prosecuted with Vigor, and in which so many Princes and States are concerned as well as our selves, a War in which we have great Prospect of Success both by Sea and Land, and by which in all likelyhood the Tyrant's Power will be broken, and the Nation secured from him and his Successors; these fine-spun Politicians would have us return to his Friendship <hi>gratis,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a King from him, let in his Troops, and be at his Mercy: And with such a Blunder as this, they represent their Pretended King, as beginning his Harangue to his <hi>Quondam</hi> Subjects, to perswade them to play the Fool and become so again.</p>
            <p>It's as silly to put these Words into his Mouth, <hi>We come to Deliver our Subjects from the Oppressions they lye under.</hi> What part of the People of <hi>England</hi> lye under any Oppressions from the present Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? Taxes given by Parliament were never accounted Oppressions, for they are legally due. If they are now somewhat greater than ordinary, 'tis a sign indeed how desirous the People are to return to their Allegiance, when they give such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Summs of Mony to Support the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment under their present Majesties, in oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the late King and all his Adherents. To ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50509:5"/>any thing else under this Government, that looks like Oppression, is to Rave. And if any such thing were,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quis tulerit Gracchos de Seditione querentes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They complain that the People were <hi>Cheated into the late Revolution by the Arts of ill Men, and by the Prince of</hi> Orange<hi>'s Declaration, which was then taken upon Trust, but was False in all its parts, and contain'd Promises which were never intended to be perform'd.</hi> It's a strange unaccountable degree of Impudence, that some Men arrive at, and I am apt to think the Pen-men of this Declaration are second to none, who have the face to affirm publickly that the Prince's Declaration was False in all the parts of it; whereas the whole Nation knows, that it consisted of a Scheme of the late King's Mis-government, and enumerated the several Methods that were taken by him, and his Evil Counsellors, to Subvert the Laws and Religion of this Nation; all which Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods there mentioned, were in every Particular not only true, but were notoriously known to the whole Nation so to be, and were indeed the only things that justified and warranted what was then done; and to say those things are False, shows how Lamentably our Traytors are put to't for Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, since they are forc'd to make such palpable Lyes their Refuge. As for the Promises, which they say were never intended to be performed, I should return them an Answer, if the Authors of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50509:6"/>the Declaration had mentioned, or if I my self could have called to mind any thing that look'd like a Breach. But till then it may be enough to put them in mind of the late King's Promise upon his first Accession to the Crown, and of his Promise at his Coronation, which was solemnly Sworn to, and to appeal to their own Consciences how well either of them were kept.</p>
            <p>One would have thought, that in a Declaration pretended to have been emitted by a Prince, from whom his Subjects had withdrawn their Allegiance for his Male-Administration, to perswade and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them to receive him again, and re-admit him into the Government, something should have been said, either to justifie those Proceedings for which they took Offence at him, or to excuse them, and promise amendment for the future. But no such thing is so much as offer'd at in this Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So far from that, that the Revolution is ascribed to an <hi>Ambitious Design of the Prince of</hi> Orange, and an <hi>Infatuation</hi> upon the People. They make the King say, That <hi>when he heard of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Design of the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>of Invading the Kingdoms, be refused the French King's Assistance, and cast himself wholly upon the Courage and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of his English Army.</hi> And this they call <hi>Taking things from the Beginning.</hi> Whereas if they would really have <hi>taken things from the Beginning,</hi> they ought to have begun
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50509:6"/>with the Late King's Raising Money without Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Parliament,</hi> with the <hi>barbarous Murders</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the <hi>West</hi> by his Orders, with the bare-fac'd setting up for <hi>Popery,</hi> his Erecting <hi>illegal Judicatures,</hi> suspending the Execution of <hi>Laws,</hi> filling <hi>Church-Benefices,</hi> and <hi>Courts of Judicature,</hi> with such persons as would be subservient to the carrying on of his <hi>Designs,</hi> without any regard to their <hi>Integrity</hi> or <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,</hi> the <hi>invading</hi> the <hi>Rights</hi> of <hi>all Corporations</hi> by <hi>Quo Warranto</hi>'s, and <hi>Surrenders of Charters,</hi> in order to the <hi>packing</hi> such a <hi>Parliament</hi> as might subvert the <hi>Government</hi> under a <hi>Colour of Law;</hi> And to make <hi>good</hi> these <hi>bold Attempts</hi> upon the <hi>People,</hi> his raising a <hi>Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army</hi> in time of <hi>Peace,</hi> without <hi>Authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> which was neither better nor worse than vvaging a <hi>War against his own People.</hi> Had not these, and many such Enormities been committed during that short Reign of his, whatever Ambitious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> might have conceived, the <hi>late King</hi> would have retained <hi>his Soveraignty</hi> to this Day. But the <hi>Government</hi> being such, as the <hi>People</hi> found themselves not safe under it, as neither en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the Benefit of the <hi>Laws</hi> for the <hi>present,</hi> and having nothing in <hi>prospect</hi> but <hi>an Entail of Popery and Slavery upon them,</hi> and <hi>their Posterity;</hi> they were very ready to lay hold of the <hi>Deliverance</hi> which God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty presented them with, and with open <hi>Arms</hi> received the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> as being sent, and so he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50509:7"/>was, by <hi>Almighty God,</hi> upon as <hi>Glorious an Errand</hi> as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Man had the Honour to be imploy'd in, to wit, the <hi>Rescuing an Oppressed People from the Jaws of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</hi> Their complying with the <hi>Prince,</hi> in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting him to <hi>promote the Ends of his Declaration,</hi> which if they had neglected to do, they had been most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ungrateful to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Him,</hi> wanting to <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves and their Posterity,</hi> and the <hi>Just Scorn of Mankind;</hi> is by the <hi>Authors</hi> of this <hi>Declaration,</hi> most <hi>impudently</hi> ascribed to <hi>an Infatuation</hi> upon them. Which is a pretty odd way of <hi>Perswading a Nation to Receive a Dispossessed Prince again,</hi> to call them <hi>Fools for Rejecting him,</hi> without making any <hi>Enquiry into,</hi> or offering at any <hi>Answer</hi> to the <hi>Known Reasons</hi> for which they did it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Prince of Orange's Expedition</hi> is term'd an <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural</hi> Design of Invading the Kingdom. The Prince had no Design of Invading the Kingdom, but could not come over with any Safety, without such a <hi>Strength</hi> as might be <hi>able to defend him</hi> against an <hi>Illegal Force</hi> raised here. But the terming of his Design <hi>Unnatural,</hi> because, forsooth, of the <hi>Relation</hi> he has to the <hi>Late King</hi> by <hi>Blood and Marriage,</hi> proceeds from the silly <hi>Conceptions</hi> of those <hi>Narrow-spirited Mortals,</hi> who cannot distinguish betwixt a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily;</hi> and think a <hi>whole Nation</hi> ought to <hi>perish,</hi> rather than a <hi>Nephew</hi> and <hi>Son in-Law</hi> should <hi>save it,</hi> whether his <hi>Uncle</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> will or no: Not to mention the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50509:7"/>
               <hi>Concern</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> had upon him, by Reason of his ovvn <hi>Interest</hi> in the <hi>Succession.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To defeat this <hi>Unnatural Design, the Courage and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of the</hi> English <hi>Army,</hi> was what the <hi>Authors</hi> of <hi>this Declaration</hi> tell us the <hi>Late King</hi> relied on. Whereby they make him own, as the <hi>truth is,</hi> that his <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Carriage</hi> towards his <hi>People</hi> had been such, as he conceived he had but <hi>little Reason</hi> to rely upon them. And if then they saw Cause to desert him, when his <hi>Reliance and Dependance,</hi> next under God, was an <hi>Army of their own Countreymen,</hi> how much <hi>less Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> have they to receive him again now, when they see he relies upon an <hi>Army of Forreigners, Professed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies</hi> to the <hi>Nation,</hi> and <hi>Subjects</hi> to a <hi>Prince,</hi> whose <hi>Power</hi> and our <hi>Safety</hi> are things incompatible.</p>
            <p>They tell us, that when the King had Notice of the Prince's Design, <hi>he took what care he could to prevent the Mischief, by undeceiving the People, though he was not believed, till it was too late: That the Infatuation being such as to take hold of the Vital Parts of the Kingdom, and spread it self through his Army, his Court and Family, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution coming on so fast, that he found himself wholly in his Enemies Power, it was time for him to consult the Safety of his Person, by withdrawing from the Guard of Forreigners that was set upon him, and arriving in</hi> France, <hi>the only place in</hi> Europe <hi>to which he could retire with safety.</hi> And this withdrawing himself in the Circumstances he then was, the Penmen of the <hi>Declaration</hi> make him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50509:8"/>of, for being construed <hi>by the Prince of</hi> Orange<hi>'s Faction in</hi> England, <hi>to be an</hi> Abdication; <hi>a word, when applied to Sovereign Princes, that never signified any other than a Voluntary Resignation of a Crown, as in the Case of the Emperour</hi> Charles <hi>the Fifth, and the late Queen of</hi> Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den The Convention that did this, they call, a <hi>Company of Men illegally met together;</hi> and make an hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous Out cry, that <hi>they, who by their own confession, had no Power to charge the least Subject of the Realm (for it was before they had Voted themselves a Parliament), should yet destroy the whole Constitution of the Government, to make an Aucient Hereditary Monarchy turn Elective; and settle the Succession in so odd and extravagant a manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Design of this long Discourse is to show, <hi>That the King's absenting himself out of the Kingdom, when he apprehended himself not safe in it, was improperly term'd an</hi> Abdication; <hi>and that the Convention had no Authority to do what they did.</hi> To the latter of which I shall say nothing but this, That enough has been said alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to Vindicate the <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and that they have been proved abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be warranted <hi>by the Laws of this Realm,</hi> and the <hi>Practice of their Ancestors</hi> in the like Cases; and have since been Justified and Declared to be Legal by a Parliament called according to Form. And that if all that were wanting, yet there was, and is another Law, Superiour and Antecedent to <hi>the Municipal Laws
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50509:8"/>of Nations,</hi> call'd, <hi>the Law of Nature,</hi> and <hi>Right Reason,</hi> which such abject Souls as the Penmen of this <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> are endowed withal, are not acquainted with, by which it is not only Lawful, but a Duty incumbent upon all Nations, to provide for their own Safety and Security by the best and most pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential Methods, that it shall please God to direct them to, when the <hi>Government is off the Hinges,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever becomes, or however they shall think fit to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of those <hi>Princes,</hi> whose <hi>exorbitant Abuse</hi> of the <hi>Legal Power committed to them,</hi> has brought them into Disorder and Confusion.</p>
            <p>As for the Word <hi>Abdication;</hi> indeed our Lords and Commons did not think convenient to consult <hi>Grammarians,</hi> and <hi>little Pedantick Scholars,</hi> about <hi>the Propriety</hi> of a Word, when the <hi>Safety of a Nation</hi> was at stake. They did a Just, Lawful, Honourable, and Necessary Work, and made use of such Expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as they thought fit. But the Penmen of this <hi>Declaration,</hi> if at least they have informed themselves in some measure, of <hi>the common acceptation</hi> of the Word out of some Civil-Law <hi>Lexicon;</hi> do not understand, or industriously conceal how the Convention used and applied it. They do not call the King's <hi>bare withdrawing himself,</hi> an <hi>Abdication;</hi> the Words of their Vote run thus; <hi>viz. That the late King</hi> James, <hi>having by the Advice of</hi> Jesuits, <hi>and other Wicked Men, broken the Original Contract betwixt King and People, and endeavoured
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50509:9"/>to subvert the Fundamental Laws of the Realm, and since withdrawn himself, hath</hi> Abdicated <hi>the Government,</hi> &amp;c. So that <hi>the Abdication</hi> relates to <hi>the whole, his endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to subvert the Fundamental Laws,</hi> as well as <hi>his with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing himself.</hi> And a <hi>Prince</hi> may properly be said <hi>to waive,</hi> or <hi>forego his Legal Authority;</hi> when by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring <hi>to subvert the Laws,</hi> upon which it is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he assumes <hi>to himself</hi> an <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> and <hi>Tyrannical Power</hi> instead thereof: If the Convention thought fit to call this an <hi>Abdication,</hi> all Men, but <hi>Pedants,</hi> and Men of <hi>Dictionaries,</hi> will allow such Assemblies to conceive <hi>their Votes</hi> in <hi>their own Expressions,</hi> nay tho they should proceed so far, as to stamp a New Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon an Old Word. I will not say, that King <hi>James</hi>'s forfeiting his Crown by his Misgovernment, and their deposing him for it, was <hi>what he did,</hi> and <hi>what they meant,</hi> however they <hi>thought fit to express them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves;</hi> But this I know, that the <hi>Scots</hi> spoke plain <hi>English.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One Observation more I must make upon this <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph;</hi> to wit, <hi>That when the late King thought fit to leave</hi> England, He look't upon <hi>France,</hi> as <hi>the only Part in</hi> Europe, <hi>to which he could Retire with safety.</hi> By which we see, how much <hi>that Prince</hi> is in the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest of <hi>his People,</hi> who could think Himself safe no where else, but with their Mortal Enemy.</p>
            <p>In the next <hi>Paragraph,</hi> the Penmen of the <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> put us in mind, <hi>how little the Kingdom is a Gainer by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50509:9"/>the Change;</hi> and instance in <hi>Three Particulars,</hi> wherein they would have us <hi>think our selves Losers by the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain;</hi> viz. <hi>The expence of</hi> English <hi>Blood, The Loss of Ships, and The sums of Money that have been drain'd from us.</hi> They mention to us, <hi>how great things might have been done with the expence of so much Blood as has been shed in this War;</hi> but do not tell us, <hi>what things, in particular, we might reasonably expect would have been attempted to have been done.</hi> And we <hi>know very well,</hi> that there was not then, nor is now, any other occasion of Expence of <hi>English</hi> Blood, but to pull dovvn a Tyrant, vvhom the Friendship and Alliance of our Tvvo Late Kings, rais'd to such a <hi>Heighth of Power,</hi> that neither We, nor any Nation about him, can have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Prospect of Security, till it be abated. 'T is Ridiculons to say, <hi>We should not have had a</hi> French <hi>War, if we had kept the late King.</hi> For He vvould have been grovving in <hi>Strength,</hi> till We, tyed up vvith our King's <hi>Alliance with Him,</hi> from <hi>Checking Him in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer,</hi> should have become an easie <hi>prey</hi> to Him. His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Friendship to King <hi>James,</hi> vvere a miserable Security for <hi>the Nation to have relied upon.</hi> We knovv <hi>how much</hi> English <hi>Blood</hi> vvas shed in a late Reign, to destroy a Protestant State; and by <hi>whose Counsels those Two Mischievous Wars</hi> vvere set on foot; And may guess by <hi>that,</hi> vvhich vvay <hi>the Power</hi> of <hi>this Nation</hi> vvould be turned, if <hi>somebody had tht Ordering</hi> of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. As for <hi>the Loss of Ships,</hi> and Payment of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50509:10"/>they are both the Necessary Concomitants of a War. And notwithstanding the <hi>Loss of some Ships,</hi> which is to be lamented, <hi>as a Loss to the Nation,</hi> such is the Care of the Government, that the <hi>Navy is in as good,</hi> if not <hi>a better</hi> Condition than ever. As for Money, the People of <hi>England</hi> have never been unwilling, under former Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, to be at the Charge of their Deliverance; nor ever grudg'd to pay <hi>Taxes,</hi> when the Exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of a good Government required it. Nor are they so void of common Sense, as to return to <hi>Slavery to save Charges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Next Paragraph in the Declaration, is Railing and Prophecy; <hi>Usurper, Nero, Fraud</hi> and <hi>Violence:</hi> And <hi>that the Beginning of Tyranny will prove the mildest part of it.</hi> But His Majesty is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their Scolding; and for their Prophecy, we are willing to appeal to the Event.</p>
            <p>Then they advise us to consult the Benefit of our <hi>Posterity,</hi> and tell us, That if it should hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, <hi>as one of the severest Judgments of God upon this Nation, that the late King should not be restored during his Life, yet an Undoubted Right to the Crown would sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive in his dearest Son the Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>and his Issue, and such other Sons, as (the Queen being now with Child) he may happen to leave behind him:</hi> And they tell us upon this occasion, what Calamities
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50509:10"/>the <hi>Commons</hi> underwent by <hi>plunder</hi> and <hi>free quarter</hi> in the Contention betwixt the two Houses <hi>of York and Lancaster;</hi> and that such struggles will always be, where there is an <hi>injur'd Right,</hi> and <hi>an unjust Possession.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Argument here is no other than this, <hi>viz.</hi> It is the Interest of the People of <hi>England</hi> to Restore King <hi>James,</hi> and undo again the present Settlement, for fear of a Civil War, God knows when, to be occasioned by the Late King's Male Issue, vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their pretended Right. VVe must return to Slavery, for fear of a Civil VVar; that is, to all the Calamities that being conquer'd can bring upon us, rather than run the hazard of being engaged in a VVar in our own defence. But God be praised, a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil VVar upon that score is very remote in prospect. For who should abet the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> his Title? Our Malecontents are too inconsiderable a body of Men, to give the Government any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbance. They have not been able to do it all this while, notwithstanding the difficulties we have strug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> notwithstanding their Encouragement and Assistance from <hi>France.</hi> VVhat will they signifie when all things being quiet at home, and the <hi>French</hi> power broken abroad, (which these very few days last past are so happy a <hi>prelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> to,) they shall be left alone to assert the Title of a Popish young Prince, whom the Nation does
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50509:11"/>not know nor so much as believe to be any prince at all. But bloody VVars, <hi>the extirpating of many No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Families</hi> by <hi>Executions</hi> and <hi>Attainders, Plunder</hi> and <hi>Free-quarter</hi> of and upon the <hi>Commons,</hi> ensuing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Contentions betwixt the Houses of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaster.</hi> That is in a great measure true: But those two Famllies were not of a different Religion, no dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents nor fears of Innovations under <hi>either of</hi> them; no Arbitrary power dreaded: The Princes of those two Lines were both very powerful by their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest in the Nobility and Body of people: VVhereas the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> his Interest will be, if any where, amongst a very few Grumblers only; whom all considering persons must needs be asham'd to side with, considering how unsuccessful they are in all their Attempts; and how fatal it has been but within these few days to a very great Prince, to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himself to be fool'd into their Cause.</p>
            <p>The pen-men of the Declaration, in their next Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, out-do themselves in Folly and Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy: They remind how great Advantages might have been had against the <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> and what an opportunity there was of <hi>enlarging the bounds of the Christian Empire, greater than any that ever were since the declining of the Roman,</hi> if this present War had not been; which they would insinuate to us has been occasioned merely by the Late King's being disposses'd of his Power. To believe which we
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50509:11"/>must take for granted that the <hi>French</hi> King has enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in this Quarrel, out of pure good Nature to his injur'd Ally; and that if their Late King <hi>James</hi> had continued in his Government, <hi>Europe</hi> would have been at a perfect Peace within it self. But we all know that the <hi>French</hi> King for Thirty years last past has neglected no opportunities to disturb the peace of <hi>Europe;</hi> that his aiming at an Universal We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stern Empire, has occasioned all the Convulsions that so great a part of <hi>Europe</hi> has undergone in all that time. That <hi>England</hi> was capable of putting a stop to his Ambitious Designs; and that he, being very sensible of it, cultivated an Allyance with our two last Kings, to tie up the Hands of the <hi>English</hi> Nation from obstructing his Growth: That under a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant and an Heroical Prince, a Prince deservedly his Enemy, because he is the Enemy of Mankind, <hi>England</hi> would be let loose upon him (as we see at this day to his Sorrow.) And therefore it was that he struck in with the Interest of the Late King, knowing that under his Government, we should not be capable of molesting him. So that it is the <hi>French</hi> King's Ambition, and not King <hi>James</hi>'s Abdication, that is the cause of the War. O, but the <hi>Christian Empire</hi> might have been enlarged. Who should enlarge it? The <hi>French</hi> King? Who contracted an Allyance with the <hi>Grand Seignor,</hi> and encouraged him to make War upon the Christians, who in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50509:12"/>thereunto sent him Officers, Soldiers and Enge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers to instruct his people in the Art of War? Or might the Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> have been more at leasure to do it, if he were not engaged as he is in the Confederacy against <hi>France?</hi> Besides that the Supposition is wild and extravagant, how sensible a thing is it, That a Western Protestant Kingdom should be perswaded to let in Popery and Slavery, that <hi>Eastern</hi> Papists may be more at leisure to fight against the <hi>Turks?</hi> Such fulsome Non-sence do those Men accost us with, and would have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that such trash was emitted by the Late King's Order; whom if they had that Honour for, which they pretend to have by Asserting his Title so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defatigably, they would not have cast such a ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish upon his Understanding, as to ascribe such a Paper as this to him: At least not to have inserted so silly a thing as this in it.</p>
            <p>While the Late King remains unrestor'd, they tell us, <hi>no prospect of a Peace is capable of being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; but that being done, the thing will be easie, and he will use his endeavour with the Most Christian King to effect it.</hi> I thank God the Nation is not yet so weary of the War as to accept of a peace upon those Terms. Nor have we any reason to believe that whenever it shall please God to send us peace, we shall be beholden to the most Christian King for it.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50509:12"/>The Destruction of his Navy will in a great measure disable him from <hi>giving peace to Christendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing that occurs is their forbidding us to <hi>contribute to the support of the present Government by collecting or paying Taxes,</hi> &amp;c. But it will be time enough for them to command that, when their King is in possession of some part of the Kingdom again; then he may forbid them that are under his power to pay Taxes to any other. Till then the people will pay to the powers in being. And they have the less reason to expect our obedience to this part of their Declaration, because I cannot learn that any of their own Faction here in <hi>England</hi> refuse to pay their Taxes imposed by this Government: They would do well to set us a good Example. But instead of that, in direct opposition to and in contempt to their Master's Authority, some of them contribute to the support of the Government more than we do, by paying double.</p>
            <p>But to show how merciful a Prince their Master, tho the whole Nation has offended him, he will not be revenged upon all of it: Some shall survive his Indignation, that he may not be without Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. He therefore excepts only,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>About Thirty Persons by name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>All such as offered personal Indignities to him at</hi> Feversham.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50509:13"/> 3. <hi>All those, who as Judges, Jury-Men, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise acted in the barbarous Murders of Mr.</hi> John Ash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Cross, <hi>or any others that have suffered for their Affection and Loyalty to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Spies and such as have betray'd his Councels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Such as shall appear in Arms against him at his Landing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Such Magistrates as shall not cause his Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be published upon the receipt of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Goalers of Prisons, that do not Discharge out of Custody all persons committed for their Loyalty to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All others how guilty soever they may have been, shall have their pardons under the Broad-Seal of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>and the Parliament shall have it recommended to them, to pass an Act of Indemnity for quieting the minds of all People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that pen'd this Declaration take upon them very freely to hang and save whom they please; and well they might, if their game had been so sure as they apprehended. They thought their Design so laid, as there was no room left for Fortune; nay scarcely for Providence to blast it. We know what they had in prospect; to see the Late King Land at the Head of betwixt Twenty and Thirty Thousand <hi>French, Irish</hi> and <hi>Scotch.</hi> The <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet destroy'd,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50509:13"/>and ours betray'd into their Hands: An Insurrection here to join with their King, and bring him to his Palace: The Army to revolt: The Queen to be sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and the King assassinated: And all this so laid, as to be design'd to be effected at one and the same time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Enemies said, I will pursue, I will overtake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. cap. 15. v. 9.10, 11.</note>
               <hi>I will divide the spoil; my Lust shall be satisfied upon them: I will draw my Sword, my Hand shall destroy them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou didst blow with thy Wind: The Sea covered them: they sank as Lead in the mighty Waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who is like unto thee, O Lord, amongst the Gods! Who is like unto thee! glorious in Holiness, fearful in Praises, doing Wonders!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Officers and Soldiers of the Army that will quit the Ʋsurper's Service, and return to their Duty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>shall have all their Arrears paid them: And the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners shall be transported to their own Countries, or whither they shall reasonably desire.</hi> This perhaps, it would be in the Late King's power to perform, if he were once got into possession of the publick Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue. But who shall pay the <hi>French</hi> King the vast Expence of this War, which he has engaged in for King <hi>James</hi> his Restoration? Will those Arrears be remitted, or must we, who are <hi>pretended</hi> to be <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd</hi> already under this pretended <hi>Tyranny,</hi> come under <hi>real Oppressions,</hi> under a <hi>Tyranny</hi> truly and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50509:14"/>properly so called: and have all we have taken from us, and little enough too, to repay the <hi>French</hi> King's Charges for above three years War, and the loss of so many of his Subjects, and now of late for the loss of his Fleet, or must our Fleet be delivered to him in lieu of his own, which has been lost in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended King's Service? They that advice us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the King again in order to save Charges by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Peace, and think we cannot but be induced thereunto by casting up our Accounts, and perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how much we are loosers by the Bargain, may assure themselves, that, though we have not cast up this Account (because it exceeds our Arithmetick) yet we are very well apprized that it will amount to an infinite Summ; and are not so madd as to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Cause and pay Costs.</p>
            <p>The farther they proceed the more ridiculous they grow. <hi>The Church of</hi> England <hi>as established by Law, is to be protected in all its Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, and upon the Vacancies of all Spiritual Livings and Dignities in the King's Disposal, they shall be filled up with the most worthy Persons of their own Communion. And Liberty of Conscience shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to the Parliament to be establisted by Law, as a lasting Blessing to these Kingdoms.</hi> VVhat would the Nation have more? The Great <hi>Lewis the</hi> 14<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. who has extirpated the Protestant Religion in his own Kingdom; is for the Church of <hi>England</hi> here in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50509:14"/>this. The late King, who endeavoured the <hi>Subversion</hi> of it, and in a manner openly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own'd the <hi>Protection</hi> of it whilst he was here, not only by the whole Course of his <hi>Actions</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> but by disowning himself to be the Head of it, by Discountenancing the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> and submitting himself to another Head in <hi>Spirituals,</hi> will upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Steer another Course, and <hi>Protect</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> as Established by Law; and his Word must be taken for it now, tho a more Sacred thing than the Word of a King could not bind him heretofore. He that in <hi>Ireland</hi> shew'd sufficiently what he would do in <hi>England,</hi> as soon as he should have Power, contrary to what he there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised as Solemnly as he can do by any Words that the <hi>Pen-men</hi> of this <hi>Declaration</hi> are able to put into his Mouth (as any Man may be informed, that will take the pains to read that excellent Book of Dr. <hi>King</hi>'s, who was an Eye-witness of his Conduct there) will recede from his <hi>Principles</hi> an Act contrary to his own Nature here, and that in Favour of a People, against whom he is Exasperated to the utmost Degree of Extremity; and upon whom he will have it in his Power to execute his Revenge, if ever by the Power
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50509:15"/>of <hi>France,</hi> he should come to be re-instated in the <hi>Government.</hi> The very naming of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which was so Odious to him formerly, and is much more so now, that he looks upon them as Men, who by their Carriage to him at the time of the late <hi>Revolution,</hi> contradicted their own <hi>Principles,</hi> and are no longer to be trusted and relied upon by him, yet must be supposed so Silly, as to believe him upon the bare Words of a <hi>Declaration,</hi> Published, in all likelyhood, without his Order, or so much as his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>They make him promise, That <hi>Vacancies of Livings in his Disposal, shall be fill'd up by the most worthy Men in the Communion of the Church of</hi> England. But they tell us not who they are that must Judge of their Worthiness. And we know that if he receives Characters of them, from such as recommended Men to him formerly, to be prefer'd both in Church and State, we are like, for the most part, to see Men advanced to Livings and Dignities in the Church, that are and will be a Scandal to their own Communion.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:50509:15"/>
            <p> As for <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> that Doctrin Sounds so Vilely from <hi>St. Germains,</hi> that it's an Insufferable Imposition upon our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings to mention it.</p>
            <p>In the two last Paragraphs they promise for him, That he shall <hi>Restore the Navy and Stores to the Condition they were in when he left them, To Increase the Trade and Bullion of the Kingdom, and Spend the Remainder of his Reign (as he always design'd since his first coming to the Crown) in advancing the Greatness of the Monarchy, and settling it upon its true Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Ʋnity and Affections of the People.</hi> Then (as having given Reasons sufficient to draw the People over to him again, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered all Objections to the contrary) they threaten such as shall yet remain <hi>Obstinate,</hi> with <hi>falling under the Severity of his Justice,</hi> and being <hi>accountable to God for the Blood that shall be shed in this Quarrel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These are all the Arguments, Promises and Threatnings made use of in that long <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration;</hi> which are such as in my Opinion, the <hi>Declaration</hi> it self might very well have been spared; for those few that are already in the late King's Interest, needed no <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:50509:16"/>to invite them to return to their <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance;</hi> and such as adhere to the <hi>Present Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> which (God be thanked) is infinitely the greater part of the People, do so upon <hi>Principles</hi> which are not shaken in the least, nor indeed so much as touch'd upon in this <hi>Declaration.</hi> But for Fashion-sake a <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> must be had, and for Fashion-sake I have made some <hi>Observations</hi> or <hi>Reflections</hi> upon it; which how inconsiderable soever they may be, cannot possibly be so weak as their Subject.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:50509:16"/>
            <head>Books Printed for and Sold by <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-lane.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE First, Second, Third and Fourth Volumes of <hi>Mercurius Reformatus,</hi> or the New Observator: Containing Reflections upon the most Remarkable Events, falling out from time to time in <hi>Europe,</hi> and more particularly in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Appendix to <hi>Mercurius Reformatus,</hi> or the New Observator, by the same Author.</p>
            <p>State Tracts: Being a further Collection of several Choice Treatises relating to the Government; from the Year 1660 to 1689. Now published in a Body, to shew the Necessity, and clear the Legality of the Late Revolution, and Our Present Happy Settlement, under the Auspicious Reign of Their Majesties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The State of <hi>Savoy:</hi> In which a full and distinct Account is given of the Persecution of the Protestants by means of the French Councils. With the Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable Conditions and Demands that the <hi>French</hi> King would have put on the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and of the Just Causes and Motives, that induced that Duke to break off from the <hi>French</hi> Interest, and joyn with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates. Together with the most Memorable Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences that hath since happen'd there. As also the True Copies of all the Letters and Dispatches that passed between them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mathematical Magick:</hi> Or the Wonders that may be performed by <hi>Mechanical Geometry.</hi> In two Books, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Mechanical Powers</hi> and <hi>Motions.</hi> Being one of the most Easie, Pleasant, Useful (and yet most neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected) part of the Mathematicks. Not before treated of in this Language. By <hi>J. Wilkins,</hi> late Lord Bishop of <hi>Chester.</hi> The Fourth Edition.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50509:17"/>
            <p> A New, Plain, Short and Compleat <hi>French</hi> and <hi>English Grammar;</hi> whereby the Learned may attain in few Months to Speak and Write <hi>French</hi> Correctly, as they do now in the Court of <hi>France;</hi> and wherein all that is Dark, Superfluous and Deficient in other <hi>Grammars,</hi> is Plain, Short and Methodically supplied. Also very useful to Strangers that are desirous to learn the <hi>English Tongue:</hi> For whose fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is added a Short, but very Exact <hi>English Grammar.</hi> The Second Edition. By <hi>Peter Berault.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Cabinet Open'd: Or the Secret History of the Amours of Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> King. Translated from the <hi>French</hi> Copy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bibliotheca Politica:</hi> Or a Discourse by way of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, Whether Resistance of the Supream Power by a whole Nation, or People, in Cases of the last Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, can be justified by the Law of Nature, or Rules of the Gospel, Dialogue the Third. Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin:</hi> Where also is to be had the First and Second.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Gentleman's Journal:</hi> Or the Monthly Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellany. By way of Letter to a Gentleman in the Country. Consisting of <hi>News, History, Philosophy, Poetry, Musick, Translations,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>May</hi> 1692.</p>
            <p>Where are also to be had Journals for <hi>January, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary, March</hi> and <hi>April.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>